Gregory Darnell

Lewis-Sigler Institute Phone: (617) 851 9752

Carl Icahn Laboratory Email: gdarnell@princeton.edu

Princeton, New Jersey 08544 Home: http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~gdarnell/

Ph.D. Dissertation Research

The promise of curing many human diseases has become within reach as a result of development in gene-editing techniques such as CRISPR. However, before creating therapeutic techniques it is necessary to understand the genetic architecture of complex traits. My dissertation research develops novel statistical and machine learning techniques for understanding genotype-phenotype associations in complex traits such as: autoimmune diseases, gene expression, and tissue morphology. My results have shown that by properly controlling for confounding, it is possible to maintain interpretability, increase statistical power, and gain insight into the genetic architecture of complex traits.

Education

2014-2019	Ph.D. Quantitative and Computational Biology	Princeton University
2015	M.A. Quantitative and Computational Biology	Princeton University
2013-2014	Ph.D. Student Computational Biology & Bioinformatics	Duke University
2008-2013	B.S. Computer Science, <i>minor</i> Bioinformatics	University of California, Los Angeles,

Publications

Journals

- [1] Bianca Dumitrascu, **Gregory Darnell**, Julien Aroyles, Barbara E Engelhardt. "Statistical tests for detecting variance effects in quantitative trait studies." *Bioinformatics*. July, 2018
- [2] **Gregory Darnell**, Stoyan Georgiev, Sayan Mukherjee, Barbara E Engelhardt. "Adaptive Randomized Dimension Reduction on Massive Data." *Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR)*. 18(140):1-30, 2017
- [3] **Gregory Darnell**, Dat Duong, Buhm Han, Eleazar Eskin. "Incorporating Prior Information into Association Studies." *Bioinformatics*. 28(12):i47-53, *Special Issue of the Proceedings of the Nineteenth International Conference on Intelligent Systems in Molecular Biology (ISMB-2012)* Long Beach, CA: July 15-27, 2012

Archival

*Indicates equal authorship.

- [1] Jordan Ash*, **Gregory Darnell***, Daniel Munro, Barbara Engelhardt. "Joint analysis of gene expression levels and histological images identifies genes associated with tissue morphology." *arXiv preprint arXiv:458711*. October, 2018
- [2] Li-Fang Cheng, **Gregory Darnell**, Corey Chivers, Michael E Draugelis, Kai Li, Barbara E Engelhardt. "Sparse Multi-Output Gaussian Processes for Medical Time Series Prediction." *arXiv preprint arXiv:1703.09112*. March, 2017

Professional Experience

2019–2020 Institute Postdoctoral Fellow, **ICERM**, **Brown University** (Sept - June)

Institute for Computational and Experimental Research in Mathematics

Model and dimension reduction in uncertain and dynamic systems

2017 Research Internship, Microsoft Research New England (Sept - Dec)

Mentors: Dr. Nicolo Fusi

Project: Automated machine learning using parameter-free optimization

2016 Research Internship, Microsoft Research New England (June - Sept)

Mentors: Professor Jennifer Listgarten and Dr. Nicolo Fusi

Project: Output warping for improved prediction in machine learning models

2012 Research Assistant, Rockefeller University (June - Sept)

Mentors: Professors Robert Darnell and Chaolin Zhang Projects: Accurate and efficient RNA-Seq read mapping & Prediction of binding specificity of RNA-binding proteins

2009 Research Assistant, Harvard School of Public Health (June - Sept)

Mentor: Professor Alkes Price

Project: Geographical ancestry prediction using principal components analysis

on genotypes

2008–2013 Research Assistant, University of California, Los Angeles

Mentor: Professor Eleazar Eskin

Projects: Improving power in association study methods in Bioinformatics &

Data compression schemes in computational genetics

Invited Talks

• "The path to exciting research directions and fulfilling mentorship in Bioinformatics" UCLA Bioinformatics Graduation Keynote Speaker. Los Angeles, California. June 7, 2017

• "Winner's Curse in Quantitative Genomics Studies" Biological Data Science. Cold Spring Harbor, NY. Oct 28, 2016

• "Winner's Curse in Quantitative Genomics Studies" New York Area Population Genomics Workshop 2016. Princeton University, NJ. Jan 21, 2016

Teaching

Summer 2016 Computer Science: Undergraduate Mentorship Princeton University

Project: Analyzing the link between ancestry and morphology in

sea urchin embryo images

Fall 2015 COS 513: Foundations of Probabilistic Modeling Princeton University

Assistant in Instruction

Fall 2014	COS 375: Computer Architecture and Organization	Princeton University
	Assistant in Instruction	
Spring 2012	Computer Science CM124. Computational Genetics	University of California,
	Grader, Homework office hours, Test administration	Los Angeles

Technical Reviewing

2016, 2017, 2018 Reviewer for the journal of *Bioinformatics*, Oxford Academics.

Academic Awards & Accreditations

- Selected for Institute Postdoctoral Fellowship at ICERM, 2019 (Institute for Computational and Experimental Research), Brown University
- Selected for the 2017 NBA Hackathon, New York, NY
- Travel Fellowship to ISMB 2012, Long Beach, CA
- Microsoft Certified Professional, 2006
- COMPTIA A+ (Hardware and Software), 2006
- COMPTIA Network+, 2006

Skills

Python, PyTorch, Keras, R, C++, C, Java, MATLAB, Linux/Unix

Leadership

- Student leader of statistics/machine learning reading group at Princeton.
- Co-founder and president of the UCLA Powerlifting Club Sport Team.